Guide to the Neil Hughes Sandinista poster collection, 1979-1985 MS2240
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Neil Hughes Sandinista poster collection
1979-1985
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Hughes, Neil C.
MS2240
3 Linear Feet 7 Tubes
The Frente Sandinista de Liberacion Nacional is a Nicaraguan party, which ruled Nicaragua from 1979-1990 after the overthrow of the Somoza dictatorship. The collection consists of 71 posters and 2 banners illustrating various aspects of their political program.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains 71 items from the era of Sandinista rule in Nicaragua, 69 of which are posters and two of which are banners. Fifty-five posters and the two banners are unique designs, with the remaining 14 posters being duplicates. The posters were produced by various branches of the Sandinista movement. A significant amount of the posters come from the propaganda wing of the Frente Saninsta de Liberacion Nacion (F.S.L.N) or the Sandinista National Liberation Front. The collection also includes posters from the Central Sandinista de Trabajadores (Sandinista Worker's Federation) and the Cruzada Nacional de Alfabetizacion (Nicaragua Literacy Campaign). Several of the posters include portraits of Augusto Sandino, the Sandinistas' inspiration, and Carlos Fonseca, one of the founders of the F.S.L.N., as well as a couple that reference Vladimir Lenin.
Biographical / Historical
The Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional (F.S.N.L.) or Sandanista National Liberation Front was founded in 1961 in Nicaragua. They took their name from the Nicaraguan rebel Augusto Sandino who fought the U.S. occupation of Nicarague and was killed in 1934. They struggled against the ruling Somoza dictatorship until it was overthrown in 1979. In 1979, after the F.S.L.N waged a successful guerilla campaign against Somoza, a five member Junta de Gobierno de Reconstrucción Nacional (Junta of National Reconstruction) was formed which ruled until 1985, although the F.S.L.N. had effective control over the country during that period. In 1985, Daniel Ortega, a leader in the F.S.L.N., was elected president of Nicaragua.
One of the major initiatives undertaken by the Sandinistas while they were in power was an initiative to promote literacy, the Cruzada Nacional De Alfabetizacion. This initiative lowered the overall illiteracy rate from 50.3% to 12.9% in the first five months. The Sandanistas, however, had to deal with armed opposition from U.S. backed contras during their rule in Nicaragua. Due to this opposition and a stagnating economy, the F.S.L.N. was unable to win the presidential election held in 1990 and were removed from power. The party continued in opposition to the government and eventually regained the presidency in 2006.
Nicaragua -- Politics and government -- 1979-1990 -- Posters; Nicaragua -- History -- Revolution, 1979 -- Art and the revolution.; Frente Sandinista de Liberación Nacional -- Posters; Hughes, Neil C.
- Asociacion de Mujeres Nicaraguenses Luisa Amanda Espinoza, "Asamblea Constitutiva, Por La Paz Y La Defensa De La Revolucion Avanza Mujer Con Tu Participacion", December 5 & 6, 1981 (Tube 1, Poster 1)
- Asociacion de Mujeres Nicaraguenses Luisa Amanda Espinoza, "Construyendo La Patria Nueva Forjamos La Mujer Nueva", undated (Tube 1, Poster 2)
- Asociacion de Mujeres Nicaraguenses Luisa Amanda Espinoza, "Resistiremos Con Dignidad ¡Venceremos!", 1984 (Tube 1, Poster 3)
  General
  currently missing
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "2o Festival De Los Trabajadores ' Martires Y Heroes Del 27 De Enero", May 3, 1981 (Tube 1, Poster 4, Poster 5)
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "Carlos Fonseca Amador", undated (Tube 1, Poster 7, Poster 6)
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "Commandante Julio Buitrago Urroz", undated (Tube 1, Poster 9, Poster 8)
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "Educacion Popular Basica De Adultos", undated (Tube 1, Poster 10)
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "Hacia Un Premero De Mayo, Impulsando En Todos Los Frentes, Las Tareas De La Revolucion, Popular Sandinista", undated (Tube 2, Poster 12, Poster 11)
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "Jose Benito Escobar", undated (Tube 2, Poster 13)
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "Julio ¡Sandino Siempre!", undated (Tube 2, Poster 15, Poster 14)
- Central Sandinista De Trabajadores, "Lenin", undated (Tube 2, Poster 16)
- Centro Ecumenico Antonio Valdivieso, " No A La Intervenencio En Centroamerica", 1983 (Tube 2, Poster 17)
- Comite Nicaraguense Por La Paz, "Conferencia Continental Por La Paz Y La Soberania En Centroamerica y El Caribe", 1983 (Tube 2, Poster 18)
- Coordinadora Sindical De Nicaragua, "Defendemos La Ptria Por La Construccion Del Socialismo!", May 1, 1982 (Tube 2, Poster 19)
- Coordinadora Sindical De Nicaragua, "La Causa De Lenin Vive Y Triunfa, 22 De Abril. 112 Aniversario Del Natalicio De Lenin", 1982 (Tube 2, Poster 20)
- Corporacion De Minerales no Metalicos Adscrita A Inmineh, "1er Aniversario De Comnomet", February 15, 1981 (Tube 3, Poster 21)
- Corporacion Nicaraguense De Minas, "1er Aniversario De La Nacionalizacion De Las Minas, 2 De Nov. 1979-1980", November 2, 1980 (Tube 3, Poster 23, Poster 22)
- Cruzada Nacional De Alfabetizacion, "2o Congreso Nacional De Alfabetizacion, Heroes y Martires Por La Alfabetizacion", September 5 & 6, 1980 (Tube 3, Poster 24)
- Cruzada Nacional De Alfabetizacion, "Con La Solidaridad Internacional: Queremos El Apoyo Mundial, Queremos Aprender A Leer Y Escribir, Nicaragua Confia En Tu Ayuda", undated (Tube 3, Poster 25)
- Cruzada Nacional De Alfabetizacion, "El Deber De Un Hombre Es Estar Alli, Donde Es Mas Util - Jose Marti", undated (Tube 3, Poster 26)
- Cruzada Nacional De Alfabetizacion, "En Cada Rincon Liberado Un Nica Alfabetizado", undated (Tube 3, Poster 27)
- Cruzada Nacional De Alfabetizacion, "Let's Teach Our Brothers, Let's Help Each Other", 1980 (Tube 3, Poster 28)
- Cruzada Nacional De Alfabetizacion, "Solidaridad internacional con Nicaragua Alfabetizacion nuestro pueblo pide ayunda para su segunda Liberacion", undated; Series 1 Ministerio de Educaion posters (Tube 3, Poster 29)
- Del Comite Nicaraguense De Solidarida Con Los Pueblos, "1er Aniversario, 4 De Octubre", undated (Tube 3, Poster 30, Tube 4, Poster 31)
- Direccion Politica Del E.P.S., "2de Septiembre, Dia Del Ejercito Popular Sandinista", September 1985 (Tube 4, Poster 32)
- Direccion Politica E.P.S., "Por La Patria, Por La Paz, Por El Futuro...!!!", 1985 (Tube 4, Poster 33)
- F.S.L.N., "Cada Minuto Que No Hacemos Nada, Nos Solidarizamos mas Con El Enemigo...", undated (Tube 4, Poster 34)
- F.S.L.N., "Fiel Al Juramento De Patria Libre Morir", December 27, 1980 (Tube 4, Poster 35)
- F.S.L.N., "La Puntualidad Es Caracteristica Del Trabajador Sandinista...", undated (Tube 4, Poster 36)
- F.S.L.N., "Levantar La Produccion Es Parte De La Victoria!!!", undated (Tube 4, Poster 37)
- F.S.L.N., "Muerte Al Imperalismo" [Blue], undated (Tube 4, Poster 38)
- F.S.L.N., "Muerte Al Imperalismo" [Green], undated (Tube 4, Poster 39)
- F.S.L.N., "Muerte Al Imperalismo" [Orange], undated (Tube 4, Poster 40)
- F.S.L.N., "Muerte Al Imperalismo" [Red], undated (Tube 5, Poster 41)
- F.S.L.N., "Nicaragua Territoria Victorioso Sobre El Analfabetismo", August 23, 1980 (Tube 5, Poster 42, Poster 43)
- F.S.L.N., "No Producimos Herramientas; Debemos Cuidar Las Que Tenemos...", undated (Tube 5, Poster 44)
- F.S.L.N., "¡Nuestro Pueblo Vencera!", undated (Tube 5, Poster 45)
- F.S.L.N., "Organizacion...Para Salvar Nuestra Vida", undated (Tube 5, Poster 46)
- F.S.L.N., "Platiquemos Menos Trabajermos Mas...", undated (Tube 5, Poster 47)
- F.S.L.N., "Resistiremos... Y Venceremos!!!", undated (Tube 5, Poster 48)
- F.S.L.N., "Sandino Vive En La Lucha Por La Paz!", undated (Tube 5, Poster 49)
- F.S.L.N., "Todos Tenemos Un Puesto En La Defensa De La Patria!!", undated (Tube 5, Poster 50)
- F.S.L.N., "Un Solo Ejercito En La Defensa Y La Produccion", undated (Tube 6, Poster 51)
- Instituto Nicaraguense De Communicaciones Y Correos, "Carlos...Estamos Cumpliendo", undated (Tube 6, Poster 52)
- Instituto Nicaraguense De Minas E Hidrocarburos, "1er Aniversario De La Nacionalizacion De Las Minas", November 2, 1980 (Tube 6, Poster 53, Poster 54)
- Jornadas Populares De Salud, "Prevenir La Malaria Es Mejor", undated (Tube 6, Poster 55)
- Junta De Gobierno De Reconstruccion Nacional, "7 De Noviembre De 1976 - 7 De Noviembre De 1979" (Tube 6, Poster 56)
- Juventud Sandinista 19 De Julio, "MPS Universidad, undated (Tube 6, Poster 57, Poster 58)
- Ministerio De Culture, "Jornada De La Independencia Cultura 'Ruben Dario'", 1984 (Tube 6, Poster 59)
- "Nicaragua, Central America, You'll Love It!", undated (Tube 6, Poster 60)
- "Nicaragua, Central America, Eight Vacations in One", undated (Tube 7, Poster 61)
- Nicaragua Inturismo, "Dia De Liberacion: 19 Julio 1979", undated (Tube 7, Poster 62)
- Nicaragua Inturismo, "El Toro - Guaco", undated (Tube 7, Poster 64, Poster 63)
- Nicaragua Inturismo, "Monimbosenos", undated (Tube 7, Poster 66, Poster 65)
- "Nicaragua, Patria Del General De Hombres Libres", undated (Tube 7, Banner 1)
- "Solidaridad Con Nicaragua, Paz Si, 1984, Chantajes No" (Tube 7, Poster 67)
- "¡Somos Hijos De Sandino Y Bolivar! Bicentenario Del Nacimiento Del Libertador Simon Bolivar", undated (Tube 7, Poster 68)
- "¡Todas Las Armas Al Pueblo!", 1983 (Tube 7, Poster 69)
- Union Nacional De Empleados, "Carlos Fonseca, Siempre En La Lucha Por La Eficiencia Y La Austeridad", undated (Tube 7, Poster 70, Poster 71)
- "Viva Nicaragua Libre! 19 Julio 1979, Patria Libre O Morir", undated (Tube 7, Banner 2)